<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://dylansec-ar.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://dylansec-ar.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2026-01-27T18:57:51+00:00</updated><id>https://dylansec-ar.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>Portfolio </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Hardware</title><link href="https://dylansec-ar.github.io/blog/2026/Hardware/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Hardware"/><published>2026-01-25T15:16:00+00:00</published><updated>2026-01-25T15:16:00+00:00</updated><id>https://dylansec-ar.github.io/blog/2026/Hardware</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://dylansec-ar.github.io/blog/2026/Hardware/"><![CDATA[<p>Guiding Hardware Selection and PC Builds for Optimal Performance In my ongoing efforts to support friends with their tech needs, I’ve taken on the role of a hardware consultant and builder. For instance, when a friend wanted a gaming rig that could handle future upgrades without breaking the bank, I researched components like CPUs (For example,AMD low-medium tier Ryzen processors for efficiency), GPUs (deciding by brand, cost, benchmark comparson, energy consumption, etc.), RAM (by price, speed, clock, and brand reliability), and storage (nowadays picking only NVME SSD for raw speed efficiency and price, HDD still an option for bulk storage). I prioritized future-proofing by selecting motherboards with extra RAM/M.2 slots. Once selected, I either assembled the PC myself. Handling cable management, thermal paste application, and BIOS setup or provided step-by-step remote guidance via video calls, troubleshooting issues like boot failures in real-time. This process not only ensured the builds met specific needs but also taught me about compatibility pitfalls, such as mismatched RAM timings (which makes the faster ram loosen its timing until both are equal) Outcomes included fully functional systems that performed better than off-the-shelve options for the exact purposes intended and saved money to the buyers.</p> <p>My own computer was the first ever experience i had with building computers, in late 2021 i started studying and learnt a lot about how should i build it for my purpose (high school studying and light gaming). While i wanted light gaming i understood that a graphics card would make the whole build future proof so i researched what should i get, the best options were gtx 1060 - 1660, etc. In the end i decided to go with an at the time newly released component, AMD Ryzen 5 5600G with vega integrated graphics, This was the most sound choice given that there was a severe GPU shortage. the rest of the computer was made around it.</p> <ul> <li>GPU: AMD Vega 8 Graphics / Later upgraded to MSI Armor RX 580 8GB VRAM 2304SP</li> <li>CPU: Ryzen 5 5600G</li> <li>RAM: 16GB DDR4 3200Mhz Cl16</li> <li>Storage: 2TB HDD / 500GB M.2 NVME (SSD)</li> <li>Motherboard: Gigabyte A520M DS3H</li> <li>PSU: Gigabyte P550B (550w)</li> </ul> <p>The hardest “issue” i had to troubleshoot was the processor - motherboard chipset incompatibility, i knew about this before i bought the motherboard, because AMD ryzen series 5000 processors were new, i knew most motherboard manufacturers would have to update the firmware, so i got the A520M DS3H specifically because it had the Q-FLASH Plus feature, which allowed updating without a secondary compatible processor.</p> <p>Other builds i made were Two computers for my sisters:</p> <ul> <li>GPU: Ryzen Vega 8 Graphics</li> <li>CPU: Ryzen 5 5600GT</li> <li>RAM: 16GB DDR4 3600Mhz cl18</li> <li>Storage: 1TB M.2 NVME (SSD)</li> <li>Motherboard: Gigabyte B550M</li> <li>PSU: Thermaltake smart 600w</li> </ul> <p>A computer overhaul for an internet friend (of which building process i supervised through video call).</p> <ul> <li>GPU: RX 570 4GB VRAM -&gt; RX 6600XT 6GB VRAM</li> <li>CPU: Intel i7 5th generation -&gt; Ryzen 5 5500</li> <li>RAM: 8GB DDR3 -&gt; 16G DDR4</li> <li>Motherboard: ASUS H97-Plus -&gt; Asrock B550M Pro4</li> <li>New case with better airflow and modern aesthetics</li> </ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Portfolio"/><category term="Hardware"/><category term="Assist"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[PC Build]]></summary></entry></feed>