<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://dylansec-ar.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://dylansec-ar.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2026-01-30T17:43:18+00:00</updated><id>https://dylansec-ar.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>Portfolio </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Hardware</title><link href="https://dylansec-ar.github.io/blog/2026/Hardware/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Hardware"/><published>2026-01-25T15:16:00+00:00</published><updated>2026-01-25T15:16:00+00:00</updated><id>https://dylansec-ar.github.io/blog/2026/Hardware</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://dylansec-ar.github.io/blog/2026/Hardware/"><![CDATA[<p>Guiding Hardware Selection and PC Builds for Optimal Performance In my ongoing efforts to support friends with their tech needs, I’ve taken on the role of a hardware consultant and builder. For instance, when a friend wanted a gaming rig that could handle future upgrades without breaking the bank, I researched components like CPUs (For example,AMD low-medium tier Ryzen processors for efficiency), GPUs (deciding by brand, cost, benchmark comparson, energy consumption, etc.), RAM (by price, speed, clock, and brand reliability), and storage (nowadays picking only NVME SSD for raw speed efficiency and price, HDD still an option for bulk storage). I prioritized future-proofing by selecting motherboards with extra RAM/M.2 slots. Once selected, I either assembled the PC myself. Handling cable management, thermal paste application, and BIOS setup or provided step-by-step remote guidance via video calls, troubleshooting issues like boot failures in real-time. This process not only ensured the builds met specific needs but also taught me about compatibility pitfalls, such as mismatched RAM timings (which makes the faster ram loosen its timing until both are equal) Outcomes included fully functional systems that performed better than off-the-shelve options for the exact purposes intended and saved money to the buyers.</p> <p>My own computer was the first ever experience i had with building computers, in late 2021 i started studying and learnt a lot about how should i build it for my purpose (high school studying and light gaming). While i wanted light gaming i understood that a graphics card would make the whole build future proof so i researched what should i get, the best options were gtx 1060 - 1660, etc. In the end i decided to go with an at the time newly released component, AMD Ryzen 5 5600G with vega integrated graphics, This was the most sound choice given that there was a severe GPU shortage. the rest of the computer was made around it.</p> <ul> <li>GPU: AMD Vega 8 Graphics / Later upgraded to MSI Armor RX 580 8GB VRAM 2304SP</li> <li>CPU: Ryzen 5 5600G</li> <li>RAM: 16GB DDR4 3200Mhz Cl16</li> <li>Storage: 2TB HDD / 500GB M.2 NVME (SSD)</li> <li>Motherboard: Gigabyte A520M DS3H</li> <li>PSU: Gigabyte P550B (550w)</li> </ul> <p>The hardest “issue” i had to troubleshoot was the processor - motherboard chipset incompatibility, i knew about this before i bought the motherboard, because AMD ryzen series 5000 processors were new, i knew most motherboard manufacturers would have to update the firmware, so i got the A520M DS3H specifically because it had the Q-FLASH Plus feature, which allowed updating without a secondary compatible processor.</p> <p>Other builds i made were Two computers for my sisters:</p> <ul> <li>GPU: Ryzen Vega 8 Graphics</li> <li>CPU: Ryzen 5 5600GT</li> <li>RAM: 16GB DDR4 3600Mhz cl18</li> <li>Storage: 1TB M.2 NVME (SSD)</li> <li>Motherboard: Gigabyte B550M</li> <li>PSU: Thermaltake smart 600w</li> </ul> <p>A computer overhaul for an internet friend (of which building process i supervised through video call).</p> <ul> <li>GPU: RX 570 4GB VRAM -&gt; RX 6600XT 6GB VRAM</li> <li>CPU: Intel i7 5th generation -&gt; Ryzen 5 5500</li> <li>RAM: 8GB DDR3 -&gt; 16G DDR4</li> <li>Motherboard: ASUS H97-Plus -&gt; Asrock B550M Pro4</li> <li>New case with better airflow and modern aesthetics</li> </ul> <p>I also serviced computers several times, mostly my sister’s</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Portfolio"/><category term="Hardware"/><category term="Assist"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[PC Build]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">OS Transitions and Virtual Machine Setups for Enhanced Flexibility</title><link href="https://dylansec-ar.github.io/blog/2026/Virtual-machine/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="OS Transitions and Virtual Machine Setups for Enhanced Flexibility"/><published>2026-01-25T15:16:00+00:00</published><updated>2026-01-25T15:16:00+00:00</updated><id>https://dylansec-ar.github.io/blog/2026/Virtual-machine</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://dylansec-ar.github.io/blog/2026/Virtual-machine/"><![CDATA[<p>Exploring operating systems has been a key part of my self-learning. I recently migrated my laptop from Windows to Linux Mint, a process involving backing up data, creating a bootable USB via Rufus, partitioning the drive with GParted, and configuring GRUB for dual-boot. This switch improved system stability and introduced me to open-source tools like apt for package management. Building on that, I set up a virtual environment using VirtualBox, provisioning three VMs: Windows 7 for legacy software testing, Windows XP to simulate outdated environments, and Kali Linux for penetration testing exercises from my cybersecurity studies. I allocated resources (1gb for xp, 2 RAM for win7, 4 for kali linux), networked them (internal networks, isolated), and installed tools like Metasploit in Kali. This setup allowed safe experimentation, such as testing malware in isolation.</p> <div class="row justify-content-center"> <div class="col-md-12"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/LAB-DYLAN12-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/LAB-DYLAN12-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/LAB-DYLAN12-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/LAB-DYLAN12.png" class="img-fluid rounded" width="100%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="post-content" style="text-align: center;"> After networking them the only thing left was to test it by trying to reach the other virtual computers. I did this with the Kali Linux CLI, by: </div> <div class="post-content" style="text-align: left;"> <ul> <li>typing "ping 192.168.10.1" and "ping 192.168.10.3" respectively, this command uses ICMP protocol (TCP/IP internet layer).</li> <li>typing "ip neigh". This command checks the ARP table to see past connections and gives data about its state (e.g. REACHABLE, STALE, FAILED)</li> <li>typing nmap "-sV 192.168.10.1" and "-sv 192.168.10.3". Nmap is a reconaissance tool that scans for open ports by manipulating TCP handshake process</li> </ul> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Portfolio"/><category term="virtualization"/><category term="software"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Security through isolation and flexibility are some pros of using virtual machines]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">User support</title><link href="https://dylansec-ar.github.io/blog/2026/usersupport/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="User support"/><published>2026-01-25T15:16:00+00:00</published><updated>2026-01-25T15:16:00+00:00</updated><id>https://dylansec-ar.github.io/blog/2026/usersupport</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://dylansec-ar.github.io/blog/2026/usersupport/"><![CDATA[<p>A recent highlight was helping a friend access a website that loaded fine for me but errored out for him, pointing to an ISP-level DNS issue. Suspecting a block or misconfiguration, I first suggested switching to a public DNS like Cloudflare’s 1.1.1.1 via Windows Command Prompt. When he struggled with CLI, I pivoted to a simpler tool: recommending the Cloudflare WARP app, which automates DNS changes, adds encryption, and bypasses restrictions. Installation took minutes, and it fixed the problem instantly, restoring access. This incident showcased quick thinking, ruling out browser caches or VPNs first and emphasized user-centric support: adapting instructions to skill levels. It also highlighted DNS vulnerabilities, like ISP censorship, and how tools like WARP enhance privacy without complexity. The fix prevented ongoing frustration and educated him on basic networking, aligning with concepts like DNS resolution hierarchies.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Portfolio"/><category term="software"/><category term="assistance"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Software problems sometimes are complicated, and for the normal user, its difficult to understand the why of a problem. In this experience i could explain the logic behind an issue to a friend, and then we could solve it together.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Everyday IT Troubleshooting From Office Activations to Connectivity Fixes</title><link href="https://dylansec-ar.github.io/blog/2026/troubleshootings/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Everyday IT Troubleshooting From Office Activations to Connectivity Fixes"/><published>2026-01-25T15:16:00+00:00</published><updated>2026-01-25T15:16:00+00:00</updated><id>https://dylansec-ar.github.io/blog/2026/troubleshootings</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://dylansec-ar.github.io/blog/2026/troubleshootings/"><![CDATA[<p>Over the past few years, I’ve become the go-to troubleshooter for family and friends, resolving dozens of issues that mimic real help desk scenarios. My father, for example, frequently encounters Microsoft Office activation errors, often due to license key mismatches or network restrictions, which I’ve fixed by verifying product keys via command-line tools (e.g., slmgr.vbs), resetting activations, or guiding through phone-based support. Connectivity problems are another staple: slow Wi-Fi, dropped signals, or printer offline errors. Yesterday, I set up his new computer when internet access failed; I methodically checked cables, router settings, IP configurations (using ipconfig /release and /renew), and even ran network diagnostics to identify a DHCP server issue, resolving it by uninstalling and reinstalling NIC drivers. These experiences have sharpened my diagnostic approach: start with basics (like cables), escalate to software (event logs, firewalls, drivers), and end with hardware if needed (restarting router, changing NIC). In total, I’ve handled what feels like countless cases, building patience and clear communication skills.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Portfolio"/><category term="Software"/><category term="Virtualization"/><category term="VM"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Experience with virtualization and sandboxing for security and isolation purposes]]></summary></entry></feed>